In the spirit of Jacques Cousteau, who said,
إنطلاقا من روح جاك كوستو، الذي قال،
"People protect what they love,"
"يحمي الناس ما يحبون"
I want to share with you today what I love most in the ocean,
احب ان اشارككم اليوم أكثر ما احبه في المحيط،
and that's the incredible number and variety
وهو العدد والتنوع الذي لا يصدق
of animals in it that make light.
من الحيوانات الموجودة فيه التي تصنع ضوءا
My addiction began with this strange looking diving suit called Wasp;
بدأ ادماني مع بدلة الغطس غريبة المنظر هذه والمسماة بالدبور
that's not an acronym -- just somebody thought it looked like the insect.
هدا ليس إختصاراً -- فقط اعتقد شخص انها تشبه تلك الحشرة.
It was actually developed for use by the offshore oil industry
في الواقع لقد طورت للاستعمال من قبل صناعة النفط
for diving on oil rigs down to a depth of 2,000 feet.
للغوص بحفارات النفط الى عمق الفين قدما.
Right after I completed my Ph.D.,
بعد ان فرغت من العمل على الدكتوراه،
I was lucky enough to be included with a group of scientists
كنت محظوظة جدا لادرج ضمن فريق من العلماء
that was using it for the first time
كانوا يستعملونها للمرة الاولى
as a tool for ocean exploration.
كاداة لاستكتشاف المحيط.
We trained in a tank in Port Hueneme,
لقد تدربنا في صهريج في ميناء هيونم.
and then my first open ocean dive
و من ثم غطستي الاولى في المحيط الفسيح
was in Santa Barbara Channel.
التي كانت في قناة سانتا باربرا.
It was an evening dive.
كانت غطسة مسائية.
I went down to a depth of 880 feet
نزلت الى عمق 880 قدما
and turned out the lights.
و اطفات الانوار.
And the reason I turned out the lights is because I knew I would see
والسبب اني اطفات الانوار هو اني عرفت اني سوف ارى
this phenomenon of animals making light
ظاهرة الحيوانات التي تصدر ضوءا
called bioluminescence.
التي تسمى بالأضاءة الحيوية.
But I was totally unprepared
لكني كنت غير مستعدة تماما
for how much there was
لهذا الكم الموجود
and how spectacular it was.
و كيف كان رائعا.
I saw chains of jellyfish called siphonophores
رايت حلقات من قنديل البحر تسمى بسيفونوفور
that were longer than this room,
كانت اطول من هذه الغرفة
pumping out so much light
تضخ الكثير من الضوء
that I could read the dials and gauges
حتى انه كان باستطاعتي قراءة عقارب الساعة والمقاييس
inside the suit without a flashlight;
داخل السترة من غير مصباح يدوي،
and puffs and billows
ونفث و عباب
of what looked like luminous blue smoke;
ما كان يبدو مثل دخان ازرق مضيئ
and explosions of sparks
وانفجارات من الشرر
that would swirl up out of the thrusters --
تقدح من الدفع
just like when you throw a log on a campfire and the embers swirl up off the campfire,
تماما مثلما تلقي بغصن لاشعال النار فتتطاير الجمرات،
but these were icy, blue embers.
ولكن هده كانت باردة جدا، جمرات زرقاء.
It was breathtaking.
كان خاطفا للانفاس.
Now, usually if people are familiar with bioluminescence at all,
الان، عادة لو أن أحد من الناس مطلع على الإضاءة الحيوية،
it's these guys; it's fireflies.
انهم هؤلاء الشبان، هذه اليرقات (حشرات ذات ذيل يضيء باللبل).
And there are a few other land-dwellers that can make light --
كما هناك عدد قليل اخر يسكن اليابسة ويستطيع صنع ضوء،
some insects, earthworms, fungi --
كبعض الحشرات و ديدان الارض والفطريات.
but in general, on land, it's really rare.
ولكن في العموم هو نادر حقا على اليابسة.
In the ocean, it's the rule
في المحيط هو القاعدة،
rather than the exception.
وليس الأستثناء.
If I go out in the open ocean environment,
عندما اخرج الى بيئة المحيط المكشوف،
virtually anywhere in the world,
عمليا في أي مكان في العالم،
and I drag a net from 3,000 feet to the surface,
و أسحب شبكة من 3000 الى السطح،
most of the animals --
أغلب الحيونات،
in fact, in many places, 80 to 90 percent
في الواقع، في اماكن كثيرة، 80 إلى 90 بالمائة
of the animals that I bring up in that net --
من الحيوانات التي تصطادها الشبكة،
make light.
تصنع ضوءاً.
This makes for some pretty spectacular light shows.
هذا ينتج بعض عروض الضوء الجميلة المذهلة.
Now I want to share with you a little video
الان اريد ان أعرض عليكم فيلم قصير
that I shot from a submersible.
صورته من غواصة.
I first developed this technique working from a little
اولا طورت هده التقنية بالعمل في
single-person submersible called Deep Rover
غواصة صغيرة تتسع لفرد واحد يدعى روفر العميق
and then adapted it for use on the Johnson Sea-Link,
ثم هياته للاستعمال في الرابط البحري جونسن
which you see here.
الذي تشاهدونه هنا.
So, mounted in front of the observation sphere,
إذن، أمام مجال الملاحظة تم إقامة
there's a a three-foot diameter hoop
طوق يصل قطره الى ثلاثة اقدام
with a screen stretched across it.
مع شاشة تمتد فوقه.
And inside the sphere with me is an intensified camera
و معي بداخل المجال كاميرا مكثفة
that's about as sensitive as a fully dark-adapted human eye,
حساسة كعين بشرية متكيفة مع العتمة،
albeit a little fuzzy.
و ان كانت غير واضحة قليلا.
So you turn on the camera, turn out the lights.
ادن عنما تشغل الكاميرا، اطفئى الاضواء.
That sparkle you're seeing is not luminescence,
الشرر اللدي ترونه ليس ضوءا متلأليء
that's just electronic noise
أنه مجرد ضوضاء الكترونية
on these super intensified cameras.
فوق هذه الكاميرات المكثفة.
You don't see luminescence until the submersible
انت لا ترى الضوء المتلأليء حتى تبدأ الغاطسة
begins to move forward through the water,
بالتحرك قدما الى الامام،
but as it does, animals bumping into the screen
ولكن ما إن تفعل ذلك، الحيوانات التي تصطدم بالشاشة
are stimulated to bioluminesce.
تحفز لتوليد الضوء الحيوي.
Now, when I was first doing this,
الان عندما قمت بذلك لاول مرة،
all I was trying to do was count the numbers of sources.
كل ما حاولت فعله هو احصاء عدد المصادر.
I knew my forward speed, I knew the area,
كنت اعرف سرعتي، كنت اعرف المساحة.
and so I could figure out how many hundreds of sources
لذا أستطيع معرفة كم من مئات المصادر
there were per cubic meter.
هناك في المتر المكعب.
But I started to realize that I could actually identify animals
لكني بدات ادرك اني في الواقع استطعت تمييز الحيوانات
by the type of flashes they produced.
من خلال نوع الومضات التي تحدثها.
And so, here, in the Gulf of Maine
واذن، هنا في خليج ماين
at 740 feet,
تحت سبع مائة واربعون قدما،
I can name pretty much everything you're seeing there to the species level.
استطيع ان اسمي تقريبا كل التي ترونها هناك على مستوى الفصائل،
Like those big explosions, sparks,
مثل تلك الانفجارات الكبيرة، الشرر،
are from a little comb jelly,
تصدر عن هلاميات مشطية (مثل قنديل البحر).
and there's krill and other kinds of crustaceans,
و هناك الكريل وانواع اخرى من القشريات،
and jellyfish.
و قنديل البحر.
There was another one of those comb jellies.
كان هناك واحد من الهلاميات المشطية.
And so I've worked with computer image analysis engineers
و هكذا عملت مع مهندسي تحليل صور بالكمبيوتر
to develop automatic recognition systems
لتطويرانظمة تعرف تلقائي
that can identify these animals
تستطيع ان تتعرف على هذه الحيوانات
and then extract the XYZ coordinate of the initial impact point.
ومن ثم استخراج X,Y,Z التي تتناسق و نقطة الاثر الاولي
And we can then do the kinds of things that ecologists do on land,
وبمكننا بعد ذلك بالقيام بالاشياء التي يقوم بها علماء البيئة على اليابسة
and do nearest neighbor distances.
والقيام باقرب المسافات بالجوار.
But you don't always have to go down to the depths of the ocean
و لكن ليس عليك دائما ان تنزل الى اعماق المحيط
to see a light show like this.
لتروا عرض ضوء كهذا.
You can actually see it in surface waters.
يمكنك ان تراه في المياه الضحلة.
This is some shot, by Dr. Mike Latz at Scripps Institution,
هذا شريط مصور من قبل الدكتور مايك لاتز في مؤسسة سكريبس
of a dolphin swimming through bioluminescent plankton.
لدلفين يسبح عبر عوالق بحرية مضيئة حيوياً.
And this isn't someplace exotic
وهذا ليس بمكان غريب
like one of the bioluminescent bays in Puerto Rico,
مثل واحد من الخلجان ذوات الضوء المتلأليء في بورتيريكو،
this was actually shot in San Diego Harbor.
في الواقع صورت هذه في ميناء سان دييجو.
And sometimes you can see it even closer than that,
وفي بعض الاحيان يمكنك رؤيتها اقرب من ذلك
because the heads on ships --
لان الرؤوس على المراكب --
that's toilets, for any land lovers that are listening --
التي بها حمامات، بالنسبة لاي من محبي اليابسة اللذين يصغون--
are flushed with unfiltered seawater
تغسل بماء البحر الغير مصفى
that often has bioluminescent plankton in it.
اللتي غالبا ما تحتوي عوالق مضيئة حيوياً،
So, if you stagger into the head late at night
اذن اذا ما ترنحت في وقت متاخر من الليل،
and you're so toilet-hugging sick
وكنت بحاجة ماسة للذهاب الى المرحاض
that you forget to turn on the light,
حتى انك تنسى ان تضيء الانوار،
you may think that you're having a religious experience. (Laughter)
قد تعتقد انك تمر بتجربة دينية.
So, how does a living creature make light?
اذن، كيف يصنع الكائن الحي ضوءا؟
Well, that was the question that 19th century
حسنا، كان هذا هو السؤال،
French physiologist Raphael Dubois,
العالم النفسي الفرنسي للقرن التاسع عشر رافيال ديبوا
asked about this bioluminescent clam.
قد طرحه بخصوص البطلينوس ذو الضوء الحيوي.
He ground it up and he managed to get out a couple of chemicals;
طحنها و تمكن من استخراج زوج من المواد الكيميائية،
one, the enzyme, he called luciferase;
انزيم يسمى لوسيفراس،
the substrate, he called luciferin
الركيزة وسماها لوسيفرين
after Lucifer the Lightbearer.
بعد لوسيفير حامل الضوء.
That terminology has stuck, but it doesn't actually refer to specific chemicals
ترسخ هذا المصطلح، ولكنه في الواقع لا يشير الى مواد كيميائية معينة
because these chemicals come in a lot of different shapes and forms.
لأن هذه المواد الكيميائية تتخذ اشكالا مختلفة.
In fact, most of the people
في الواقع، اغلب الناس
studying bioluminescence today
الذين يدرسون الأضاءة الحيوية اليوم
are focused on the chemistry, because these chemicals
يركزون على الكيمياء لان هذه المواد الكيميائية
have proved so incredibly valuable
اثبتت انها قيمة بشكل لا يصدق
for developing antibacterial agents,
في تطوير عوامل مضادة للبكتيريا،
cancer fighting drugs,
ادوية مكافحة للسرطان،
testing for the presence of life on Mars,
إختبار وجود حياة في المريخ،
detecting pollutants in our waters --
كشف الملوثات في مياهنا،
which is how we use it at ORCA.
هكذا نستعملها في اوركا.
In 2008,
في 2008،
the Nobel Prize in Chemistry
جائزة نوبل في الكيمياء
was awarded for work done
منحت لعمل قام به
on a molecule called green fluorescent protein
حول جزئ يسمى بالبروتين الفلوري الاخضر،
that was isolated from the bioluminescent chemistry
التي تم عزلها عن كيمياء الضوء الحيوي
of a jellyfish,
لقنديل بحر،
and it's been equated to the invention of the microscope,
ويعادل هذا اختراع المجهر،
in terms of the impact that it has had
من حيث التاثير الذي لديه
on cell biology and genetic engineering.
على بيولوجيا الخلية والهندسة الجينية
Another thing all these molecules are telling us
شيء اخر تخبرنا به كل هذه الجزئيات
that, apparently, bioluminescence has evolved
هو أن الإضاءة الحيوية قد تطورت
at least 40 times, maybe as many as 50 separate times
على الاقل، اربعون مرة، ربما الى ما يصل الى خمسون مرة منفصلة
in evolutionary history,
في التاريخ التطوري،
which is a clear indication
و هو إشارة واضحة
of how spectacularly important
لمدي أهميته الشديدة.
this trait is for survival.
هذه الصفة للبقاء
So, what is it about bioluminescence
اذن ماذا بالإضاءة الحيوية
that's so important to so many animals?
من الأهمية للعديد من الحيوانات؟
Well, for animals that are trying to avoid predators
حسنا، لبعض الحيوانات التي تحاول تجنب الكائنات المفترسة
by staying in the darkness,
بالبقاء في الظلام،
light can still be very useful
مايزال الضوء مفيدا جدا
for the three basic things that animals have to do to survive:
بالنسبة للاشياء الثلاثة الاساسية التي علي الحيوانات القيام بها للبقاء،
and that's find food,
وهي ايجاد الطعام،
attract a mate and avoid being eaten.
جذب زوج و تجنب ان تؤكل.
So, for example, this fish
اذن على سبيل المثال هذه السمكة
has a built-in headlight behind its eye
لها مصباح قد ادمج وراء عينها
that it can use for finding food
تستطيع استعماله لايجاد الطعام
or attracting a mate.
او جذب زوج
And then when it's not using it, it actually can roll it down into its head
وعندما لا تستعمله تستطيع في الواقع لفه في راسها
just like the headlights on your Lamborghini.
مثل المصابيح في سيارتكم اللامبورغيني.
This fish actually has high beams.
في الواقع لدى هذه السمكة اشعاعات مرتفعة.
And this fish, which is one of my favorites,
وهذه السمكة، التي هي واحدة من المفضلين عندي،
has three headlights on each side of its head.
لها ثلاثم صابيح في كل جانب من راسها.
Now, this one is blue,
الان، هذا ازرق،
and that's the color of most bioluminescence in the ocean
وهذا هو لون اغلب الضوء الحيوي في المحيط
because evolution has selected
لان التطور قد اختار
for the color that travels farthest through seawater
اللون الذي يسافر ابعد خلال ماء البحر
in order to optimize communication.
من اجل تحسين التواصل
So, most animals make blue light,
اذن اغلب الحيوانات تصنع ضوءا ازرق،
and most animals can only see blue light,
واغلب الحيوانات لا يمكنها رؤية الا الضوء الازرق،
but this fish is a really fascinating exception
ولكن هذه السمكة هي بحق استثناء ساحر بحق
because it has two red light organs.
لان لها عضوين لضوئين احمرين.
And I have no idea why there's two,
وليس لدي ادنى فكرة لماذا هناك اثنان،
and that's something I want to solve some day --
وهذا شيء اريد يوما ما ان احله.
but not only can it see blue light,
لذا ليس باستطاعتها فقط رؤية الضوء الأزرق،
but it can see red light.
بل ايضا رؤية ضوءا احمرا.
So it uses its red bioluminescence like a sniper's scope
لذا تستعمل الضوء الحيوي الاحمر مثل جهاز رؤيا القناص
to be able to sneak up on animals
لتتمكن من التسلل علي الحيوانات
that are blind to red light
التي لا تبصر الضوء الاحمر
and be able to see them without being seen.
ويمكنها رؤيتها دون ان يروها.
It's also got a little chin barbel here
لديها ايضا ذقن صغير
with a blue luminescent lure on it
ذو ضوء حيوي ازرق كطعم
that it can use to attract prey from a long way off.
يستعمل لجذب الفريسة من بعيد.
And a lot of animals will use their bioluminescence as a lure.
و الكثير من الحيوانات سوف يستعملون ضوءهم الحيوي كطعم.
This is another one of my favorite fish.
هذه واحدة اخرى من اسماكي المفضلة.
This is a viperfish, and it's got a lure
هذة افعى الاسماك، و هي لديها طعم
on the end of a long fishing rod
على نهاية عصا طويلة للصيد
that it arches in front of the toothy jaw
تقوسه امام الفك المسنن
that gives the viperfish its name.
الذي يعطي افعى الاسماك اسمه.
The teeth on this fish are so long
أسنان هذه السمكة طويلة جدا
that if they closed inside the mouth of the fish,
لدرجة انها اذا ما اغلقت داخل فم السمكة،
it would actually impale its own brain.
سوف تطعن مخها.
So instead, it slides in grooves
لذا بدلا عن ذلك، تنزلق في اخاديد
on the outside of the head.
خارج الرأس.
This is a Christmas tree of a fish;
هذة شجرة الميلاد لسمكة.
everything on this fish lights up,
كل شيء على هذه السمكة يضيء.
it's not just that lure.
ليس فقط ذلك الطعم
It's got a built-in flashlight.
لها كشافات مدمجة.
It's got these jewel-like light organs on its belly
تمتلك اعضاء مضيئة كالجواهر على معدتها
that it uses for a type of camouflage
تستعملها كنوع من التمويه
that obliterates its shadow,
تطمس ظلها،
so when it's swimming around and there's a predator looking up from below,
لذا عندما تسبح و هناك مفترس ينظر من اسفل،
it makes itself disappear.
فأنها تخفي نفسها.
It's got light organs in the mouth,
لها اعضاء ضوء في فمها.
it's got light organs in every single scale, in the fins,
لها أعضاء ضوء في كل قشرة، في الزعانف،
in a mucus layer on the back and the belly,
في طبقة المخاط على الظهر وفي البطن،
all used for different things --
كلها تستعمل من اجل اشياء مختلفة،
some of which we know about, some of which we don't.
البعض نعرف عنه والبعض لا نعرف عنه.
And we know a little bit more about bioluminescence thanks to Pixar,
ونحن نعرف اكثر قليلا عن الإضاءة الحيوية بفضل بيكسار،
and I'm very grateful to Pixar for sharing
انا ممتنة لبيكسار لمشاركة
my favorite topic with so many people.
موضوعي المفضل مع العديد من الناس.
I do wish, with their budget,
اتمنى، من خلال ميزانيتهم،
that they might have spent just a tiny bit more money
انه ربما يستطيعون انفاق أموال أكثر قليلا
to pay a consulting fee to some poor, starving graduate student,
لدفع رسوم إستشارات لطالب دراسات عليا فقير يتضور جوعا،
who could have told them that those are the eyes
كان من الممكن أن يخبرهم ان تلك العيون هي
of a fish that's been preserved in formalin.
لسمكة حفظت في فورمالين.
These are the eyes of a living anglerfish.
هذه عيون سمكة صيادة حية.
So, she's got a lure that she sticks out
لذا لديها طعم تبرزه
in front of this living mousetrap
امام مصيدة فئران حية
of needle-sharp teeth
لأسنان حادة كالابرة،
in order to attract in some unsuspecting prey.
لكي تجذب بعض الفرائس المطمئنة.
And this one has a lure
وهذه لها طعم
with all kinds of little interesting threads coming off it.
مع كل انواع الخيوط المثيرة التي تخرج منها.
Now we used to think that the different shape of the lure
الأن كنا نعتقد ان اختلاف شكل الطعم
was to attract different types of prey,
يجذب انواع مخنلفة من الفرائس،
but then stomach content analyses on these fish
ولكن تحليل محتوى معدة هذه الاسماك
done by scientists, or more likely their graduate students,
من قبل العلماء او على الارجح طلاب الدراسات العليا،
have revealed that
كشفت أن
they all eat pretty much the same thing.
كلهم ياكلون نفس الشيء الى حد كبير.
So, now we believe that the different shape of the lure
لذا الأن نعتقد ان الشكل المختلف للطعم
is how the male recognizes the female
هو وسيلة تمييز الذكر الانثى
in the anglerfish world,
في عالم السمك الصياد،
because many of these males
لأن الكثير من هؤلاء الذكور
are what are known as dwarf males.
هم ما يعرفون بالذكور الاقزام.
This little guy
هذا الشاب الصغير
has no visible means of self-support.
ليس لديه وسائل دعم ذاتي مرئية.
He has no lure for attracting food
ليس لديه طعم لجذب الطعام
and no teeth for eating it when it gets there.
او أسنان لأكله عندما يحصل عليه.
His only hope for existence on this planet
أمله الوحيد للتواجد على هذا الكوكب
is as a gigolo. (Laughter)
أن يعرض نفسه علي الإناث.
He's got to find himself a babe
عليه ان يجد لنفسه فتاة
and then he's got to latch on for life.
تم عليه ان يتمسك بها طول حياته.
So this little guy
لذا هذا الشاب الصغير
has found himself this babe,
قد وجد لنفسه هذه الفتاة،
and you will note that he's had the good sense
وسوف تلاحظون، أن له احساس جيد
to attach himself in a way that he doesn't actually have to look at her.
ليربط نفسه بطريقة حيث ان ليس عليه في الواقع النظر اليها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But he still knows a good thing when he sees it,
ولكن هي مع ذلك تعلم انه شيء جيد عندمل يراها
and so he seals the relationship with an eternal kiss.
ولذا يتوج العلاقة بقبلة ابدية.
His flesh fuses with her flesh,
ينصهر لحمه بلحمها،
her bloodstream grows into his body,
ينمو مجرى دمها في جسده،
and he becomes nothing more than a little sperm sac.
ويصبح ليس أكثر من كيس صغير للحيوانات المنوية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Well, this is a deep-sea version of Women's Lib.
حسنا هذه هي نسخة أعماق البحار من رواية تحرر المرأة.
She always knows where he is,
هي تعرف دائما أين هو،
and she doesn't have to be monogamous,
وليس عليها ان تتزوج بواحد فقط،
because some of these females
لان بعض هذه الاناث
come up with multiple males attached.
تأتي و عدة ذكور متعلقين بها.
So they can use it for finding food, for attracting mates.
إذن يمكنها استعمالها لايجاد الطعام او جذب الازواج.
They use it a lot for defense, many different ways.
تستعملها كثيرا للدفاع بطرق مختلفة كثيرة.
A lot of them can release their luciferin or luferase in the water
الكثير منهم يستطيع ان يطلق لوسفرين و لوفيرس في الماء
just the way a squid or an octopus will release an ink cloud.
بالضبط كما يطلق الحبار او الاخطبوط سحابة من الحبر.
This shrimp is actually
هذا الروبيان في الواقع
spewing light out of its mouth
يقذف ضوءا من فمه
like a fire breathing dragon
كتنين ينفث نارا
in order to blind or distract this viperfish
لكي يعمي او يلهي افعى الاسماك هذه
so that the shrimp can swim away into the darkness.
حتى يستطيع الروبيان السباحة بعيدا في الظلام.
And there are a lot of different animals that can do this:
وهناك العديد من الحيوانات المختلفة التي تستطيع القيام بذلك.
There's jellyfish, there's squid,
هناك قناديل البحر، هناك الحبار،
there's a whole lot of different crustaceans,
هناك مجموعة كبيرة مختلفة من القشريات.
there's even fish that can do this.
حتى ان هناك سمكة تستطيع فعل ذلك.
This fish is called the shining tubeshoulder
تسمى هذه السمكة بانبوب الكتف اللامعة
because it actually has a tube on its shoulder
لانها فعلا تمتلك انبوبا فوق كتفها
that can squirt out light.
يستطيع ان يبخ الضوء.
And I was luck enough to capture one of these
و كنت محظوظة جدا للامساك بواحدة من هذه
when we were on a trawling expedition
عندما كنا في رحلة صيد
off the northwest coast of Africa for "Blue Planet,"
في الساحل الشمالي الغربي لأفريقيا ل"الكوكب الازرق"
for the deep portion of "Blue Planet."
للجزء العميق من"الكوكب الازرق"
And we were using a special trawling net
وكنا نستعمل شبكة صيد خاصة
that we were able to bring these animals up alive.
حتى نتمكن من احضار تلك الحيوانات حية
So we captured one of these, and I brought it into the lab.
فقبضنا على واحدة من هؤلاء و احضرناها الى المختبر.
So I'm holding it,
انا امسك بها،
and I'm about to touch that tube on its shoulder,
و انا أهم بلمس ذلك الأنبوب فوق كتفها،
and when I do, you'll see bioluminescence coming out.
وعندما افعل ذلك سوف ترون الضوء الحيوي يخرج منها.
But to me, what's shocking
و لكن بالنسبة لي ما كان مدهشا
is not just the amount of light,
هو ليس فقط كمية الضوء،
but the fact that it's not just luciferin and luciferase.
بل هو ان الامر لم يكن فقط لوسيفرن ولوسيفرات.
For this fish, it's actually whole cells
فلهذه السمكة، كانت في الواقع خلايا كاملة
with nuclei and membranes.
لها نوى و اغشية.
It's energetically very costly for this fish to do this,
يتطلب هذه السمكة طاقة كبيرة للقيام بذلك،
and we have no idea why it does it --
و ليس لدينا ادنى فكرة لماذا تقوم بذلك.
another one of these great mysteries that needs to be solved.
واحدة اخرى من الاحجيات الكبيرة التي تحتاج الى الحل.
Now, another form of defense
الان طريقة اخرى من الدفاع
is something called a burglar alarm --
انه شيء يسمى باندار اللصوص.
same reason you have a burglar alarm on your car;
لنفس السبب الذي يجعل لديك في سيارتك انذار للسرقة.
the honking horn and flashing lights
بوق التزمير و الاضواء الساطعة
are meant to attract the attention of, hopefully,
تهدف لجذب انتباه
the police that will come and take the burglar away --
الشرطة التي سوف تأتي و تأخذ اللص.
when an animal's caught in the clutches of a predator,
عندما يقع حيوان في براثن مفترس،
its only hope for escape may be
فامله الوحيد للهروب هو ربما
to attract the attention of something bigger and nastier
جدب انتباه شيء اضخم و اكثر شراسة،
that will attack their attacker,
سوف يهاجم مهاجمهم،
thereby affording them a chance for escape.
ومن ثم يتاح لهم فرصة الهروب.
This jellyfish, for example, has
لقنديل البحر على سبيل المثال
a spectacular bioluminescent display.
عرض مذهل للإضاءة الحيوية.
This is us chasing it in the submersible.
هذا نحن نطارده في الغاطسة.
That's not luminescence, that's reflected light from the gonads.
هذا ليس ضوءا متلأليء، هذا ضوء منعكس عن الغدد التناسلية.
We capture it in a very special device on the front of the submersible
لقد قبضنا عليه في جهاز خاص في مقدمة الغاطسة
that allows us to bring it up in really pristine condition,
الشيء الذي أتاح لنا بإحضاره في حالته الاصلية الحقيقية،
bring it into the lab on the ship.
أحضرناه الى مختبر بالقارب.
And then to generate the display you're about to see,
وثم توليد العرض اللدي انتم بصدد مشاهدته
all I did was touch it once per second
كل ما فعلته هو لمسها مرة كل ثانية
on its nerve ring with a sharp pick
على العصب الدائري بعود حاد
that's sort of like the sharp tooth of a fish.
مثل سن حادة لسمكة.
And once this display gets going, I'm not touching it anymore.
وما أن يبدأ العرض لن ألمسها مجددا.
This is an unbelievable light show.
هذا عرض ضوء لا يصدق.
It's this pinwheel of light,
أنها عجلة دوارة من الضوء.
and I've done calculations that show that this could be seen
وقد قمت بحساباتي التي أظهرت إن ذلك يمكن رؤيته
from as much as 300 feet away by a predator.
من ما يصل الى ثلاثمائة قدم من قبل مفترس.
And I thought, "You know,
وفكرت
that might actually make a pretty good lure."
أن هذا ربما يمثل في الواقع طعما جيدا.
Because one of the things that's frustrated me
لانه من الاشياء اللتي تحبطني
as a deep-sea explorer
كمستكشفة لإعماق البحر
is how many animals there probably are in the ocean that we know nothing about
كيف ان العديد من الحيوانات هناك في المحيط لانعرف عنهم شيئا
because of the way we explore the ocean.
بسبب الطريقة التي نعتمدها لاستكتشاف المحيط.
The primary way that we know about what lives in the ocean
الطريقة الاساسية لمعرفة ماذا يعيش في المحيط،
is we go out and drag nets behind ships.
هو ان نخرج ونجر الشبكات خلف المراكب.
And I defy you to name any other branch of science
وانا اتحداكم ان تسموا اي شعبة من شعب العلم الاخرى
that still depends on hundreds of year-old technology.
ما زالت تعتمد على تكنولوجيا قديمة تعود لمئات السنين.
The other primary way is we go down
الطريقة الرئيسية الاخرى هي النزول الى اسفل
with submersibles and remote-operated vehicles.
بغاطسات ومركبات تشغل عن بعد.
I've made hundreds of dives in submersibles.
قمت بمئات الغطسات في غاطسات.
When I'm sitting in a submersible though,
علي الرغم أني حين أجلس في الغاطسة،
I know that I'm not unobtrusive at all --
أعلم إني لست خفية على الاطلاق.
I've got bright lights and noisy thrusters --
لدي أضواء ساطعة و محركات دفع صاخبة.
any animal with any sense is going to be long gone.
أي حيوان واعي سيكون قد رحل منذ فترة طويلة.
So, I've wanted for a long time
لهذا أردت مند زمن بعيد
to figure out a different way to explore.
إيجاد طريقة مختلفة للإستكتشاف.
And so, sometime ago, I got this idea for a camera system.
ولذا في وقت سابق واتتني فكرة لنظام كاميرات.
It's not exactly rocket science. We call this thing Eye-in-the-Sea.
ليست بالضبط فكرة متقدمة. نسمي هدا الشيء بعين في البحر.
And scientists have done this on land for years;
ولقد قام العلماء بهذا على اليابسه لسنوات،
we just use a color that the animals can't see
نحن فقط نستعمل لون لا يمكن للحيوانات رؤيته،
and then a camera that can see that color.
و من ثم كاميرا بامكانها رؤية ذلك اللون.
You can't use infrared in the sea.
لايمكن أن نستعمل الاشعة تحت الحمراء في البحر.
We use far-red light, but even that's a problem
لقد استعملنا ضوء أحمر، ولكن هذه مشكلة ايضا
because it gets absorbed so quickly.
لانها تمتص بسرعة كبيرة.
Made an intensified camera,
تجعل الكاميرا المكثفة،
wanted to make this electronic jellyfish.
تريد ان تصنع قنديل البحر الالكتروني هذا.
Thing is, in science,
الامر انه في العلم
you basically have to tell the funding agencies what you're going to discover
عليك ان تخبر وكالات التمويل ماذا سوف تكتشف
before they'll give you the money.
قبل ان يعطوك المال.
And I didn't know what I was going to discover,
ولم أكن أعلم ما سوف اكتشفه،
so I couldn't get the funding for this.
لذا لم استطع الحصول على تمويل لهذا.
So I kluged this together, I got the Harvey Mudd Engineering Clinic
لذا جمعت هذا، وحصلت على عيادة هارفي مود للهندسة
to actually do it as an undergraduate student project initially,
للقيام به كمشروع طالب في المرحلة الجامعية،
and then I kluged funding from a whole bunch of different sources.
ثم حصلت على تمويل من مجموعة مصادر مختلفة.
Monterey Bay Aquarium Research Institute
معهد بحوث ومتحف بحري خليج مونتراي
gave me time with their ROV
منحوني الوقت مع مركبتهم التي تدار عن بعد
so that I could test it and we could figure out,
حتى يتسنى لي إختبارها و معرفة،
you know, for example, which colors of red light we had to use
على سبيل المثال، أي ألوان الضوء الاحمر يجب أن نستعمل
so that we could see the animals, but they couldn't see us --
لكي نستطيع رؤية الحيوانات في حين لا يستطيعون رؤيتنا،
get the electronic jellyfish working.
نهييء قنديل البحر الالكتروني للعمل.
And you can see just what a shoestring operation this really was,
ويمكنكم أن تروا كم كانت هذه العملية قليلة التكاليف حقاً
because we cast these 16 blue LEDs in epoxy
لأنه عندما أدلي اللمبات الزرقاء الستة عشر في الايبوكسي
and you can see in the epoxy mold that we used,
ويمكنكم الرؤية من خلال الايبوكسي الذي استعملناه
the word Ziploc is still visible.
كلمة زيبلوك ما تزال مرئية.
Needless to say, when it's kluged together like this,
غني عن الذكر، أنه عندما جمع مع بعضه هكذا،
there were a lot of trials and tribulations getting this working.
كان هناك الكثير من المحاولات و المصاعب لجعله يعمل.
But there came a moment when it all came together,
و لكن أتت لحظة تم إلتحام كل شيء معا،
and everything worked.
و نجح كل شيء،
And, remarkably, that moment got caught on film
و بشكل ملحوظ، تلك اللقطة التقطت في فيلم
by photographer Mark Richards,
من قبل المصور مارك ريتشارد،
who happened to be there at the precise moment
الذي صادف وكان هناك في اللحظة الصحيحة
that we discovered that it all came together.
التي اكتشفنا فيها أن كل شيء يعمل.
That's me on the left,
هذا أنا على اليسار،
my graduate student at the time, Erika Raymond,
طالبة الدراسات العليا الذي أشرف عليها في ذلك الوقت، اريكا ريموند،
and Lee Fry, who was the engineer on the project.
ولي فراي، الذي كان مهندسا في المشروع.
And we have this photograph posted in our lab in a place of honor
ولقد وضعنا هذه الصورة في مختبرنا في مكان شرف
with the caption: "Engineer satisfying two women at once." (Laughter)
مع تعليق : "مهندس يرضي إمرأتين في نفس الوقت."
And we were very, very happy.
وكنا سعداء جدا جدا.
So now we had a system
فالأن لدينا نظام
that we could actually take to some place
نستطيع في الواقع ان نحمله الى مكان ما
that was kind of like an oasis on the bottom of the ocean
يشبه نوعا ما واحة في قعر المحيط
that might be patrolled by large predators.
ربما تحرسها مفترسات كبيرة.
And so, the place that we took it to
ولذا المكان الدي اخذناه اليه
was this place called a Brine Pool,
كان هذا المكان يسمى بركة المياه المالحة
which is in the northern part of the Gulf of Mexico.
الذي هو في الجزء الشمالي من خليج المكسيك.
It's a magical place.
انه مكان ساحر.
And I know this footage isn't going to look like anything to you --
و انا اعرف ان هده اللقطات لن تبدو كاي شيء لكم--
we had a crummy camera at the time --
في دلك الوقت كان لدينا كاميرا رخيصة--
but I was ecstatic.
ولكني كنت متحمسة.
We're at the edge of the Brine Pool,
كنا على حافة بركة المياه المالحة.
there's a fish that's swimming towards the camera.
هناك سمكة كانت تسبح باتجاه الكاميرا.
It's clearly undisturbed by us.
كان من الواضح انها لم تكن منزعجة منا.
And I had my window into the deep sea.
و كان لدي نافددتي الخاصة على العمق.
I, for the first time, could see what animals were doing down there
استطعت لاول مرة ان ارى ما تفعله الحيوانات هناك بالاسفل
when we weren't down there disturbing them in some way.
حين لا نكون في الاسفل نزعجهم بطريقة او بأخرى.
Four hours into the deployment,
أربع ساعات في التحضير،
we had programmed the electronic jellyfish
لقد قمنا ببرمجة قنديل البحر الالكتروني
to come on for the first time.
ليتقدم للمرة الاولى.
Eighty-six seconds after
بعد ست و ثمانون ثانية
it went into its pinwheel display,
بدأ عرضه الضوئي الدوار،
we recorded this:
سجلنا هذا.
This is a squid, over six feet long,
هذا حبار، طوله اكثر من ستة أقدام،
that is so new to science,
هذا جديدعلى العلم،
it cannot be placed in any known scientific family.
لايمكن ان توضع في اي عائلة علمية معروفة.
I could not have asked for a better proof of concept.
لا يمكنني أن أطلب دليل أفضل من هذا علي صحة مفهوم.
And based on this, I went back to the National Science Foundation
و بناءاً على هذا عدت بادراجي الى مؤسسة العلوم الوطنية
and said, "This is what we will discover."
وقلت، "هذا ما سوف نكتشفه"
And they gave me enough money to do it right,
وقد زودوني بالمال الكافي للقيام به على الوجه الصحيح،
which has involved developing the world's first deep-sea webcam --
والتي شملت تطوير اول كاميرا لإعماق البحر في العالم،
which has been installed in
والتي تم تثبيتها في
the Monterey Canyon for the past year --
مونتري كانيون العام الماضي.
and now, more recently,
و الأن في الاونة الاخيرة،
a modular form of this system,
وحدات من هذه النظام،
a much more mobile form
قابلة للحركة بشكل أكبر،
that's a lot easier to launch and recover,
هذا اسهل بكثير في الإطلاق والإستعادة،
that I hope can be used on Sylvia's "hope spots"
وأمل أن تستعمل في "نقاط الامل" لسيلفيا
to help explore
لتساعد على إستكتشاف
and protect these areas,
وحماية هده البقاع،
and, for me, learn more about
وبالنسبة لي، التعلم اكثر عن
the bioluminescence in these "hope spots."
الضيائية الحيوية في "نقاط الامل."
So one of these take-home messages here
إذن واحد من الرسائل هنا هو
is, there is still a lot to explore in the oceans.
هناك الكثير لنكتشفه في المحيطات،
And Sylvia has said
و قالت سيلفيا
that we are destroying the oceans before we even know what's in them,
اننا ندمر المحيطات قبل حتى ان نعرف ماذا فيهم،
and she's right.
وهي محقة.
So if you ever, ever get an opportunity
لذا لو صادف وسنحت لك الفرصة
to take a dive in a submersible,
للقيام بالغطس في الغاطسة،
say yes -- a thousand times, yes --
قل نعم، الاف المرات، نعم،
and please turn out the lights.
أطفإوا الأنوار من فضلكم.
I promise, you'll love it.
اعدكم بانكم سوف تحبونها
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)